And actually, some of the things I say in my writings, where I say strategy is what you do,
not what you say, right? So most, I ignore most statements about strategy and annual reports and
the like, because they mainly are exaggerated, delusional, you know, whatever. I just,
you see, written by corporate affairs-type people. I just watch what they do and say, oh, oh, that's,
that's your strategy. Your strategy is what you do. And so, Dad's strategy was, was what he did.
He may not have called at that, because like me until I got to Harvard Business School, I didn't
know this thing existed. Yeah. If our listeners here, we have some listeners who might be going,
okay, well, what does he mean by that? What's Roger on about there? Tell us a little bit more.
Well, here's the, here's the thinking. And my, my specific definition keeps it kind of evolving a
little, a little bit. But what, what I, what I say is the, you know, a company, Goldman,
Westpac, these big companies were, where you work, have lots and lots of resources,
and they control lots and lots of things. How many people do we employ? What do we pay them?
How many factories or branches or whatever to have? How much advertising to do? How much R&D to do?
All sorts of things that are under their control. But there's this one, like really,
really important thing that is not under their control. And that's what customers do.
And either pull a wad of cash out of their pocket and give it to you, or give it to somebody else.
So the purpose of strategy is to make an integrated set of choices that compels desired customer
action, right? So all you have to make choices in all the areas in which you can make choices,
you're empowered to make choices because, because these things are under your control.
And you want those choices as a whole, a complete unified coherent whole to land with the customer
in a way that the customer says, I'll, I'll take one of those, right? And, and if it doesn't land
in that way, who gives a damn what choices you made? And that's why it's not a planning
document. It's not a list of laudable, sensible things. Like most, I would say only 10 to 15% of
companies, let's say S&P 500-sized companies or FTSE 100-sized companies,
only 10 or 15% of them have an integrated set of choices that compels customer action.
The rest of them have a laundry list of things that went to the manufacturing person and say,
what would you like? Oh my God, I've worked somewhere like that. I won't say where, but I,
there is, I heard I was listening to you going for a walk there and I knew we're talking to Tiffany
Bova. Oh, yeah. And I loved this because this links to what you just said there. And I actually
wrote it down. I actually, I really listened to it about six times ago. I got to write this down now,
because what you said was so good. I've actually WhatsApp this to quite a few people. The currency
of planning is initiatives. The currency of strategy is choices. Rather than a list of initiatives,
it is an integral set of choices that have to fit together and reinforce each other. And these
choices need to compel the customer to take action you want. Do you know the other phrase I love from
you? And I don't think you get enough credit for this phrase because I've heard this phrase about
3000 times in my career, particularly was used in Westpac all the time. What would have to be true
for this option to work? I'm telling you, if you are making money after that phrase, you better go
down to Sydney in Australia, because that phrase is used in Westpac all the time. And I never knew
it came from you. Yes. No, it did. It did. Although I've heard it attributed to others,
and I've had people, people correct them to say no, no. If I hear anyone say it now,
I say, oh, Dr. Martin, yes, yes. Do you want to know where it came from? I do.
It's a necessity is the mother of invention. So it's 1992. I'm in a hotel in Rhinelander,
Wisconsin. Four Seasons? No, not a Four Seasons. It was like a Days Inn or something. But it was the closest
hotel to a mine called Copper Range, which is on the southern shore of Lake Superior. And that is
absolutely the middle of nowhere and really harsh, harsh environment. And so it is made Rhinelander,
I don't know, maybe it's 20,000 person town. But this was the closest hotel there because
the assignment I was working on was a strategy for the future of Copper Range, the Copper Mine.
And it was a Toronto company called Inmet Mining. And there were six people from head office that had
come. And six people had driven down a couple of, it was probably three or four hours from the
mine site, the guys who were running the mine. And the problem was the problem of a teak was,
it had once been a great mine because the part of the mine that they mined first,
the Copper Grade was really good. And so hauling ore with Copper in a long way to the nearest
Smelter and Refiner was no problem. But as the grade got lower and you were shipping a ton of
rocks with a tiny little bit of Copper in it and become uncompetitive. So the question was,
but there are still lots of Copper in the mine. So the question was, do you build a Smelter and
Refiner at Copper Range at the site? So you don't have any virtually no transportation costs of raw
ore, you're just transporting Copper and you can ship Copper anywhere you want pure Copper,
it's cost effective. Or do you shut it down? And so it was a two day off site where I was to work
with these two teams, the joint team to come up with an answer for the CEO. All day long, first day,
the people, the six people from the mine are, build the Smelter and Refiner, the Toronto guys,
close it down. Build, close, build, close, build, close, build, close, build, close,
eight hours of build, close, build, close, build, close. And I'm like, so we end the day and I know
we're going to go back the next day, I go back to my room in this Motel 6 and I'm thinking,
you know what, Roger? Tomorrow is going to be build, close, build, close, build, close, build,
close, build, close. And everybody's already getting a little hot under the collar because
we're not making any progress and I can't see any progress. And so I said, I've got to do
something else, then, then ask what they think is true. Because the miners think what's true is that
we could spend the $2 billion to do this and then we could be smelting and refining copper from
this mine for the next 25 years or whatever. And the others are saying, kind of what is true is
this is the pipe dream. They'll never pay off at copper prices in the copper grade,
whatever, never pay off $2 billion investment would be nice. And so I said, what if, rather than
having them argue because they're they're completely on other sides on what they think is true,
why don't I ask, what would have to be true for them to build the smelter and refiner,
Marie, what would have to be true for them to put their hands on their heart and say,
nope, sorry, we got to close it. So that was it. And I went, I went the next morning and said,
listen, we're going to do this little experiment. Okay. And so, and we'll flip the coin as to who
which we'd tackle first, but we're going to ask the question, what would have to be true? Like,
what would have to be true about copper prices, the cost of building, blah, blah, blah, blah,
what, what set of things would have to be true for all 12 of us to put our hands on our hearts and say,
build. And then we're going to do, and one order or the other, we're then going to do this,
or what would have to be true for all 12 of us to put our hands on our hearts and say,
so the right answer is, is close close to town. Within an hour, within an hour,
we had a what would have to be true for build with everybody signing off of it.
If these things were to be true, we would say build, close the same thing. And then,
because I was on a roll then, I then asked the next question. One of those things that would
have to be true are you most worried are not true. And they quickly identified it. Oh, circle this
one, circle this one. And on this side, circle this one, circle this one. We come out with a work
plan that says we've got to look more closely at those four, those two things for the build case,
those two things for the close case, we went off, did some work. A couple months later,
they went with a unanimous decision to corporate leadership, unanimous 100% everybody.
And then I said to Chris, have you got a question for Roger?
All right, here we go. So here we go. So he goes, look, he said,
he goes, can Claude or ChatGPT help global leaders take Roger's methodology and craft their
winning strategies easier and faster? And if they can, is there anything to watch out for?
There you go, Roger. What do you think of that from Chris?
Well, the thing to think about is, is just don't think about AI is a magic, magic thing where magically
it thinks like, like a human know, as a computer. And it follows a algorithm.
All right, so if you ask it a question and it's got five billion words in it,
it has to figure out which of the five billion words to draw on to provide you with an answer.
And what is the algorithm? What is sort of the core way it distinguishes among the words?
And everybody actually kind of knows the answer because everybody's had AI for the past five or
seven years, if they use, for instance, Microsoft Word, right? You start typing the first couple
letters and what does it do? Fills them in. Okay, how did it decide what to fill in?
It's the most frequent. So it is giving you the most frequent thing that you would find in a
sentence like this, the as the next word. So AI, LLM AI is a mode seeking device.
And even if the question is more complicated and the prompts are more complicated, its answer is
what's most frequent. So the tricky thing about it is, is that if you want the tail of the distribution,
you want something way out on the right tail, the better tail of the distribution way out,
and you ask AI for that, it has no way of giving you that other than to say, on this subject,
what did most people say? Well, that's not on the tail of the distribution. And so you get a modal answer
regardless. So if what you want is to find the mode faster, cheaper, and more accurately,
use AI. If you want something on the tail, don't because it's not set up to do that.
So for strategy, that is the tricky thing. If you say to AI, give me, here's my fact set,
give me the most unique solution possible. It has no way of doing that. And it just doesn't.
Some future kind of AI that's not LLM AI may be able to do it, but it's not set up to do that.
That having been said, I was just on a call this morning on a little plan I have, I don't like
the idea of giving your problem set to the AI and say, what should my strategy be? Because you're
going to get a modal strategy. And if you're doing what everybody else is doing, it's not a
distinctive strategy and it's not worth having.